{"tossups": [{"question": "This meeting affirmed the excommunication of Philip the Amorous of France, who had claimed that his wife Bertha was too fat and scandalously remarried Bertrade of Montfort. This meeting was prompted by Byzantine envoys to the Council of Piacenza earlier the same year. Robert the Monk claimed that the audience erupted into cries of \u201cGod wills it!\u201d after a speech at this meeting called for the conquest of the Holy Land. For ten points, name this 1095 ecumenical council at which Urban II roused support for the First Crusade.", "answer": "Council of<b> Clermont</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man and his brother Charles patented the oscillating steam engine. This man designed a turner that could create bedsteads four times faster than average, but he failed to make a bedstead factory in Yonkers. A company formed by this man sold Hovair systems with the Pomagalski company. At the New York Crystal Palace, this man asked for a rope holding a platform to be cut, demonstrating a safety system while he was aboard. For ten points, name this inventor of the \u201csafety elevator\u201d and namesake of the world\u2019s largest elevator company.", "answer": "Elisha<b> Otis</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One war criminal within this regime was a chaplain-turned-Chief Guard earned the epithet \u201cBrother Satan.\u201d Despite accusations that Archbishop Aloysius Stepinac collaborated with this regime, he was named a cardinal in 1952 and beatified after his death. The title of<em> Poglavnik</em> was given to the leader of this regime, Ante Pavelic [ahn-tay pav-eh-lich]. Inmates at the Jasenovac concentration camp were often killed with knives known as \u201cSerbcutters\u201d under, for ten points, what fascist regime that committed genocide in World War II-era Croatia?", "answer": "<b> Ustase</b> ([oos-ta-shuh], but be lenient; accept<b> Ustasha</b>-Croatian Revolutionary Movement)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A site-specific sculpture installed in this country at Gibbs Farm is a horn shaped steel skeleton with fabric stretched over it that runs through a hill. Anish Kapoor\u2019s<em> Dismemberment</em> is located in this country, as was a \u201ccardboard\u201d cathedral meant to replace a building that was damaged in a 2011 earthquake. Gottfried Lindauer left Bohemia to work in this country, where he painted Paratene Te Manu, a man with distinctive spiral facial tattoos. For ten points, name this country that suffered the 2011 Christchurch earthquake.", "answer": "<b> New Zealand</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {"question": "At this location, a torpedo attack caused the<em> Pallada</em> to keel over during fighting that one side initially thought was part of the celebrations for Admiral Oskar Stark\u2019s wife. Despite that confusion, the surprise attack at this location was only able to disable two battleships, the<em> Retvizan</em> and<em> Tsarevich</em>. The<em> Poltava</em> was sunk at a battle at this location on the southern tip of the Liaodong Peninsula. For ten points, name this Manchurian port that was besieged during the Russo-Japanese War.", "answer": "<b> Port Arthur</b> (accept<b> Ryojun</b>; accept<b> Lushun</b> City; prompt on Liaodong Peninsula before mentioned; prompt on Manchuria before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The original choice to govern this entity was Percy Kirke, but was replaced after his harsh response to the Monmouth Rebellion. This entity\u2019s armed forces were once led by Lieutenant Governor Francis Nicholson, until he was deposed in Leisler\u2019s Rebellion. A 1684 revolt that led to the revocation of the Massachusetts Bay Colony\u2019s charter inspired the need for this entity, which was intended to improve royal control under Edmund Andros. For ten points, name this short-lived dominion created by James II that merged colonies like New Hampshire and Maine.", "answer": "Dominion of<b> New England</b> (in America)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Hans Traxler cartoon inspired a nickname for this politician translating to \u201cpear.\u201d This man used the Basic Law to call a controversial vote of no confidence that led Karl Carstens to dissolve his country\u2019s parliament. Francois Mitterand and this man were co-awarded the Charlemagne Award for efforts in unifying Europe; those efforts were also commemorated when the first European Act of State honored this key architect of the Maastricht treaty. For ten points, name this Chancellor of Germany during its reunification.", "answer": "Helmut<b> Kohl</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a letter to Thomas Auld, this man asked how Auld would feel if this man kidnapped his daughter. This man posited that had Henry Box Brown not popularized his methods, thousands of slaves could have escaped per year. This man purposely never smiled in photographs to avoiding playing into the caricature of a \u201chappy slave.\u201d Victoria Woodhull did not consult this man before naming him her running mate in 1872.<em> The North Star</em> was edited by, for ten points, what abolitionist who wrote a<em> Narrative</em> about his life as a slave?", "answer": "Frederick<b> Douglass</b> (accept Frederick Augustus Washington<b> Bailey</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader refuted hunger strikes at Maze Prison, saying \u201ccrime is crime is crime.\u201d Ian Paisley\u2019s \u201cUlster Says No\u201d campaign attacked this leader\u2019s deal with Garrett FitzGerald that gave Ireland an advisory role in Northern Ireland. This leader won an election with the slogan \u201cLabour Isn\u2019t Working.\u201d For ten points, name this conservative Prime Minister of the UK, the first woman to hold the office.", "answer": "Margaret Hilda<b> Thatcher</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Protesters in this country adopted a salute from the<em> The Hunger Games</em>, then switched to handing out \u201csandwiches for democracy.\u201d Ten politicians in this country were removed from office over removing an officer from the National Security Council. The National Council for Peace and Order currently leads this country, where a 2014 coup led to the rise of Prayut Chan-o-cha. For ten points, name this country where that 2014 coup rocked the streets of Bangkok.", "answer": "<b> Thailand</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The Law and Order party pardoned the leader of this rebellion, who called off an attack on a local arsenal after a cannon misfired and killed a bystander. Samuel Ward King declared martial law to suppress this rebellion, which directly led to the Supreme Court case of<em> Luther v. Borden</em>. This rebellion began after its namesake organized the People\u2019s Convention in opposition to his state\u2019s charter that required land ownership to vote. For ten points, name this 1842 insurrection in Rhode Island.", "answer": "<b> Dorr</b>\u2019s Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Harsh punishments for committing this crime included Louis Mandrin\u2019s execution, by being broken on the wheel, in 1755 for performing this activity along the Savoyard border. Suppressing this activity was largely outsourced to the paramilitary General Farm, which enforced the<em> octroi</em>. This activity was widely performed on the borders of Brittany, where salt was 20 times cheaper than neighboring Maine. State monopolies were challenged by, for ten points, what activity that avoids taxes by illegally transporting goods?", "answer": "<b> smuggling</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer depicted a real-life fighter pilot who returned to the military after losing his legs in his final opera,<em> The Story of A Real Man</em>. This composer collaborated with Constructivist Georgi Yakulov on a ballet celebrating Soviet industrialization,<em> The Steel Step</em>. This composer controversially included a happy ending in a ballet whose excerpt \u201cDance of the Knights\u201d is also known as \u201cMontagues and Capulets.\u201d<em> Romeo and Juliet</em> was written by, for ten points, what Soviet composer who depicted a Young Pioneer in<em> Peter and the Wolf</em> ?", "answer": "Sergei<b> Prokofiev</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After two decades of rule from Mobile, this city was briefly the capital of French Louisiana before Nouvelle Orleans.", "answer": "<b> Biloxi</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This position has been held by two women including Miriam \u201cMa\u201d Ferguson in the 1920s and 30s. The second woman to hold this position implemented the Robin Hood plan to equalize school fundings and was criticized for claiming \u201cPrince Charming may be driving a Honda\u201d and \u201cexpect you to make the payments.\u201d That woman held this position until Karl Rove\u2019s homophobic push polls helped elect a future President to this post. For ten points, name this statewide political position held from 1995 to 2000 by George W. Bush.", "answer": "<b> Governor of Texas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A 1925 silver dollar attempted to raise funds for a project at this location, which Marvin Griffin pushed his state\u2019s legislature to buy in 1958. The Venable Brothers were once owners of this location, where August Lukeman continued a project in 1928 after it was abandoned</b> <b>by (+)</b> <b>Danish sculptor Gutzon Borglum to complete a similar work at South Dakota\u2019s</b> <b>Mount Rushmore. The second iteration of the (*)</b> Ku Klux Klan was founded at, for ten points, what mountain in Georgia on which images of Stonewall Jackson, Jefferson Davis, and Robert E. Lee are carved?", "answer": "<b> Stone Mountain</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Plutarch claims that, upon hearing the cry \u201cExcept for being king, you are not at all superior to us,\u201d this man replied, \u201cBut were I not better than you, I should not be king!\u201dThis man\u2019s son Pausanias won at the Battle of Plataea before he was accused of allying</b> <b>with (+)</b> <b>Xerxes the Great. After the Carneia, this man led forces to a battle that took</b> <b>Xerxes the Great. After the Carneia, this man led forces to a battle that took</b> <b>place simultaneously with the Battle of Cape (*)</b> <b>place simultaneously with the Battle of Cape (*)</b> Artemisium. Ephialtes [eff-ee-all-teez] revealed a secret goat path, leading to this king\u2019s death. For ten points, name this Spartan king who fended off the Immortals until the last minute at the Battle of Themopylae.", "answer": "<b> Leonidas</b> I", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The saying \u201cMahu will get you\u201d was inspired by an authoritarian overseer of this project who allegedly ate children. A summit section of this feature was created under the oversight of an engineer named Oqruqci [oak-ruk-chee]. The shipwrecked Korean official Choe (+) Bu studied this system in the 15th century during his travels from Suzhou to Tongzhou. The</b><em><b> Kaiheji</b></em><b> records the construction of this feature, which was initiated under Emperor Wen. (*)</b> Lock gates in the sixth century greatly improved the navigability of this feature, which ends in Hangzhou. For ten points, name this project, begun under the Sui [swee] Dynasty, that connected the Yellow and Yangtze Rivers.", "answer": "<b> Grand Canal</b> of China (accept<b> Beijing-Hangzhou</b> Grand<b> Canal</b> before \u201cHangzhou\u201d is read, prompt after) Page 12", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This film ends with parts of a speech that quoted Winston Churchill in saying \u201cA man does what he must... and that is the basis of all human morality.\u201d In this movie, Bruce Dern portrays a character paralyzed by a stroke who gives his son the one-word command</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>\u201calibi\u201d during a phone conversation. This movie, which ends with its main character</b> <b>receiving a suspended two-month sentence, stars Kate Mara as a woman who dies after a black (*) </b> Oldsmobile veers off a bridge. Mary Jo Kopechne drowns in, for ten points, what 2017 film named for a 1969 incident involving Ted Kennedy?", "answer": "<b> Chappaquiddick</b>  (1) <b>The subjects of this court case were taken from a property owned by Arthur</b> <b>Goldreich, one of whom was living under the pseudonym David Motsamayi. (+) Lionel Bernstein was acquitted during this event, after which Denis Goldberg was sent to a white prison. During this event, one target noted that he \u201ccherished the ideal of a democratic and free society\u201d and outlined his reasons for creating the (*) </b>Spear of the Nation in his \u201cI Am Prepared to Die\u201d speech. Leaders of the ANC were targeted in, for ten points, what 1960s trial that sentenced Nelson Mandela to life in prison? ANSWER:<b> Rivonia</b> Trial", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}